Guide to the Ann Rosener Papers M1946
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
Ann Rosener papers
circa 1900-2013
M1946
Dept. of Special Collections & University Archives
20.0 Linear feet (21 manuscript boxes; 10 flat boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, photographs, posters, exhibition catalogs, subject files, drafts, and business records documenting Ann Rosener's career as a photographer, designer, and publisher.
Rosener, Ann.
Access to Collection
The materials are open for research use. Audio-visual materials are not available in original format, and must be reformatted to a digital use copy.
Biographical Note
Ann Rosener in her long life was active as a photographer, designer, and private press publisher. She was a native of San Francisco, where her grandparents settled in the mid-19th century; her father was a civil engineer. She graduated in 1935 from Smith College, where she took poetry and literature classes that helped shape her lifelong interests.
During World War II, Rosener worked as a photojournalist in Washington for the Office of War Information. One of her assignments was to photograph women at home to show their ability to help the war effort, whether repairing vacuum cleaners or salvaging cooking grease for bombs. Her postwar portraits of Walter Gropius, Richard Neutra, Patrice Munsel, and Tennessee Williams, among others, were published in Life magazine.
In the early 1950s Rosener returned to California, settling in the Los Angeles area. She married briefly and through her husband, the art dealer Frank Perls, she met artists and collectors. She continued to work as a photographer, but in 1951 she designed a museum for the Pacific Coast Borax Company in Death Valley, and in 1956 was involved in the production of the film "Around the World in 80 Days."
After moving to the Bay Area, she worked at Stanford University from 1964 to 1988, designing exhibition catalogues and posters for the Stanford Museum of Art, as well as library bookplates and invitations to University functions.
In 1976 Rosener acquired a Vandercook press and Chandler & Price presses and began to set type by hand. Her earliest effort was the poem by W. B. Yeats "The Coming of Wisdom with Time." Only a photocopy survives, but it shows the "First proofs made on the Vandercook 4 at Occasional Works in Woodside" date from December of 1976. A few other small projects date from the late 1970s and early 1980s, when she first hand set Bembo, then bought monotype Bembo from Mackenzie and Harris. Bembo remained her favorite typeface, whether metal or digital. After she retired, Rosener became more ambitious. Four books printed on the Vandercook involved collaborations with artists, incorporating original prints or facsimile reproductions. From 1992 new projects demanded greater skills as a printer and as a publisher: a collection of poetry by C. P. Cavafy with etchings by William Brice; two complex illustrated accordion-fold books; and two anthologies of poems that not only showed her far-ranging reading but involved considerable correspondence about permissions.
Her letters demonstrate her wit and way with words. Rosener collaborated with several Bay Area printers (notably Eric Holub); for Jeff Maser, her agent and colleague, she printed a series of broadsides. She often designed papers for her book covers, and T&J Graphics in Redwood City supplied color printing as well as technical advice. From 1993 her books were bound by the Foolscap Press in Santa Cruz. Her last publications, dating from 2007–08, were significantly poetry broadsides, the last a translation of an ode by Horace that recalls the subject of the Yeats poem of 1976.
Biography from the 2013 Mills College Library exhibit, "Ann Rosener: Designer, Printer, and Publisher"— curated by Linda Brownrigg and Betsy Fryberger.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, photographs, posters, exhibition catalogs, subject files, drafts, and business records documenting Ann Rosener's career as a photographer, designer, and publisher. It includes photographs from her work for the Office of War Information, portraits of artists such as William Brice and Rico Lebrun, and photographs of family, friends, and travels. Rosener's research for the film Around the World in 80 Days (1956) is also included in the collection, as well as her photographs and design work for the Borax Museum and the Frank Perls Gallery. Other materials of interest include posters and exhibition catalogs designed for the Stanford Art Museum, Art Department, and the Stanford Development Office. The collection also contains correspondence, drafts, and business records from her private press, Occasional Works.
Arrangement
The Collection is arranged into seven series:
Series 1. Personal
Series 2. Correspondence
Series 3. Travel
Series 4. Professional
Series 5. Stanford University
Series 6. Photographs
Series 7. Artwork
Acquisition Information
This collection was given by Nancy Packer to Stanford University, Special Collections in October, 2012.
Brice, William, 1921-2008; Frank Perls Gallery.; Lebrun, Rico, 1900-1964; Neutra, Richard Joseph, 1892-1970; Occasional Works (Firm).; Pacific Coast Borax Company; Rosener, Ann.; Stanford University. Department of Art and Art History.; Stanford University. Museum of Art; United States. Office of War Information.; Book design.; Private press books--United States.
- Series 1. Personal
  Scope and Contents
  This small series contains juvenilia and miscellaneous artifacts, ephemera, and biographical materials.
  - Notes from Ann to her father, circa 1922 (Flat-box 14, Folder 1)
  - Copper printing plate (for calling card) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Phonograph records (2) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Scrap book (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Address book/journal (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Greeting cards and ephemera; includes scrap material for hand-made cards (Box 1, Folders 6-8)
  - Posters from Ann Rosener exhibit, Mills College Library 2013 (Flat-box 31, Folder 4)
- Series 2. Correspondence
  This series contains letters and cards to/from Ann Rosener. Materials sent with correspondence, such as photographs, typescripts, and clippings have been retained in this series.
  - Early family correspondence; includes letters and post cards from Ann's mother to Ann and to/from other family members; letters from Ann to her parents; also letters from miscellaneous family members, circa 1900-1925 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Eamon Grennan (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Leo Holub (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Greg Paltinger (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Eric Prokosch (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Patricia Rose (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Lawrence D. Stewart (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Dorothea Straus (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Helen Trimpi, post cards (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Susan Wilson, notes and wood engravings (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous letters to Ann Rosener (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence and holiday cards, circa 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Holiday cards, circa 1960-1970 (Box 2, Folders 12-14)
- Series 3. Travel
  This series contains materials from Ann Rosener's travels, including itineraries, travel brochures, postcards, and notes.
  - Europe, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - England, France, and Russia, circa 1970-1981 (Box 3, Folders 2-4)
  - London, 1993 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - London, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Prague, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Philadelphia, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Venice, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - England, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Paris, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - London, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - England, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - France, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Cambridge, MA (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Kyoto (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - London, miscellaneous travel material and correspondence (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - New York (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Sissinghurst Garden (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Texas (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Series 4. Professional
  This series contains materials from Ann Rosener's varied career as a designer and publisher.
  This series contains some photographs, but the majority of photographs documenting her career as a photographer have been arranged in Series 6. Design work done for Stanford University has also been arranged separately in Series 5.
  - Subseries 1. Around the World in 80 Days
    This subseries contains costume and set design research material for the film Around the World in 80 Days (1956). Also included are photographs Rosener took of actress Shirley MacLaine.
    - General notes and research (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Research; magazines and clippings (Flat-box 14, Folder 3)
    - Shirley MacLaine, casting notes (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Shirley MacLaine (photographic prints) (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Shirley MacLaine (negatives) (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - England, research notes (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - England, photostats and prints (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Paris and the balloon, research notes (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Paris and the balloon, photostats and prints (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Spain, research notes (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Spain, photostats and prints (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - S.S. Mongolia, Suez, and Indian Ocean - research notes (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - S.S. Mongolia, Suez, and Indian Ocean - photostats and prints (Box 15, Folder 12)
    - India, research notes (Box 15, Folder 13)
    - India, photostats and prints (Box 15, Folder 14)
    - Hong Kong, Singapore, and Yokohama - research notes (Box 15, Folder 15)
    - Hong Kong, Singapore, and Yokohama - photostats and prints (Box 15, Folders 16-18)
    - San Francisco to New York, research notes (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - San Francisco to New York, photostats and prints (Box 16, Folders 2-3)
  - Subseries 2. Occasional Works
    This subseries contains working files from Ann Rosener’s fine press, Occasional Works. It includes correspondence, business records, and drafts and proofs for various publications, particularly for How Words See: Some Twentieth-Century Poems about Works of Art (1998) and Sunday Collection: Thirty twentieth-century poems about Sunday (1995).
    - Correspondence, 1995-2001 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence and permissions (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Ephemera and publicity (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Miscellaneous business records (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Invoices and business records, circa 1991-2004 (Box 7, Folders 5-7)
    - Invoices, 1993 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Invoices, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Invoices, 1998-2000 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Mailing lists, circa 1985-1995 (Box 8, Folders 1-2)
    - Permissions and expenses (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Permissions (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Sales (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Thom Gunn, 1999 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - How Words See, chronologies (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - How Words See, permissions (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - How Words See, type proofs (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - How Words See, biographies and reviews (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - How Words See, poems included (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - How Words See, poems not included (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - How Words See and Sunday, business records (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Memorial poems (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Poets' cards (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Poets and poems, clippings (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Muriel Spark (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - Sunday, poems (Box 9, Folders 7-9)
    - Sunday, poems not included (Box 9, Folder 10)
    - Sunday, expenses (Box 9, Folder 11)
    - Sunday, letters and cards (Box 9, Folder 12)
    - Sunday, permissions (Box 9, Folders 13-14)
    - Thirteen Views of Santa Barbara (Edgar Bowers), jacket design, 1989 (Flat-box 26, Folder 4)
  - Subseries 3. Miscellaneous art/design projects and subject files
    This series contains materials from other miscellaneous professional projects such as design work for the Borax Museum and the Frank Perls Gallery. Also included are subject files, presumably used for design research.
    - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1961 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Design Awards (Flat-box 14, Folder 2)
    - Art gallery/museum, ephemera (Box 5, Folders 2-3)
    - Miscellaneous museum and gallery posters (Flat-box 29, Folder 3)
    - Barclay Fund, design work (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1918 book illustrations (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Borax Museum; publications, ephemera, and photographs of exhibit (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Carnegie Quarterly, 1966-1970 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Design research - acrobats (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Design research - artists' marks (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Design research - hats and wheels (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Design research - household objects (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Design research - shoes, scenic, and patterns (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Design research - writing (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Mary Hiedecker, typescripts (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Ink (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Journal of Fashion, Culture, and Fine Arts, 1895 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Journal of Fashion, Culture, and Fine Arts (photocopy), 1895 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Rico Lebrun, Crucifixion catalogue, 1950 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Letterhead design (Box 6, Folders 6-7)
    - Robert Motherwell exhibit posters, 1957 (Flat-box 31, Folders 2)
    - Frank Perls Gallery, ephemera (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Frank Perls Gallery, posters (Flat-box 29, Folder 1)
    - Type design course (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Index of typefaces (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - Printing and design samples (Box 16, Folders 4-5)
- Series 5. Stanford University, 1964-1988
  This series contains exhibit catalogues, brochures, postcards, event invitations, and posters designed by Ann Rosener for the Stanford Art Museum/Art Department, the Stanford Development Office, and other Stanford venues, such as the University Library.
  - Subseries 1. Stanford Art Museum and Art Department
    - Rodin and Balzac, exhibit catalogue, 1973 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Whistler: Themes and Variations, exhibit catalogue, 1978 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Eighteenth-Century Italian Prints, exhibit catalogue, 1980 (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Figures from Rodin's Gates of Hell, exhibit catalogue, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Robert Motherwell, exhibit catalogue jacket, 1986 (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - Richard Diebenkorn, exhibit catalogue jacket, 1987 (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Christmas card (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Ephemera (Box 10, Folders 8-11)
    - Stanford Art Museum/Department posters (Flat-box 30, Folders 1-5)
    - Stanford Art Museum/Department posters (Flat-box 31, Folders 3)
  - Subseries 2. Stanford Development Office, circa 1961-1974
    - Invitations (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Publications and ephemera (Box 11, Folders 2-7)
    - Publications and ephemera (Box 12, Folders 1-7)
    - Publications and ephemera (Box 13, Folders 1-6)
    - Stanford University Libraries, book plate designs (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Miscellaneous Stanford event posters (Flat-box 29, Folder 2)
- Series 6. Photographs
  This series contains photographic prints, negatives, contact sheets and slides from Ann Rosener's career as a photographer. Included in this series are prints from Rosener’s work for the Office of War Information; portraits of artists such as William Brice, Rico Lebrun, and Richard Neutra; photographs documenting Borax production locations and facilities; and miscellaneous travel photographs and photographs of family and friends.
  - Office of War Information, Women in Essential Service (photographic print), 1943 (Flat-box 24, Folder 1)
  - Office of War Information, Women in Essential Service (photographic prints), circa 1942-1944 (Box 17, Folders 1-3)
  - Office of War Information, Women in Essential Service (photographic prints and negatives), circa 1942-1944 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Borax Museum (photographic prints) (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Borax: photographs documenting Borax production locations and facilities; includes images of Death Valley, CA, Turkey and other locations; also construction of factory, mule team, and Boron Mine (Flat-box 25, Folders 1-5)
  - Eugene Berman (photographic prints, contact sheets, negatives) (Flat-box 23, Folder 2)
  - William Brice (photographic prints, contact sheets, negatives) (Flat-box 23, Folder 3)
  - William Brice, studio (negatives) (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Rico Lebrun (photographic prints, contact sheets, negatives) (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Rico Lebrun, Crucifixion series (photographic prints), 1950 (Flat-box 23, Folders 4-5)
  - Rico Lebrun, Crucifixion series (contact sheets and negatives), 1950 (Flat-box 23, Folder 6)
  - Walter Lodge (photographic prints and negatives), circa 1956 (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - Alvin and Elaine Lustig (negatives) (Box 19, Folder 15)
  - Richard Neutra (photographic prints) (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Richard Neutra (negatives), 1953 (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - Father McLean (photographic prints) (Flat-box 24, Folder 4)
  - Father McLean (contact sheets and negatives) (Flat-box 24, Folder 5)
  - Vincent Price and family (photographic prints and negatives), 1956 (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - Alice B. Toklas (photographic print) (Flat-box 24, Folder 7)
  - Frank Perls Gallery (photographic prints and contact sheets) (Flat-box 23, Folder 7)
  - Frank Perls Gallery (negatives) (Flat-box 23, Folder 8)
  - Claire McCardle exhibit (contact sheets), 1953 (Box 17, Folder 13)
  - Portraits of various artists (photographic prints and contact sheets) (Flat-box 23, Folder 1)
  - Family and friends (photographic prints) (Box 19, Folders 1-3)
  - Family and friends (photographic prints) (Flat-box 24, Folder 8)
  - Rosener family (photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - Ann Rosener (photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - Ann Rosener and Frank Perls (photographic prints) (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - Portrait of Ann Rosener in her press by Leo Holub (photographic print), 1978 (Flat-box 31, Folders 1)
  - Leland S. Rosener, Jr. (negatives), 1911-1912 (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - Daniel (photographic prints), circa 1954 (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - J.T., Cora, etc. (photographic prints, contact sheets, negatives), 1954 (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - Gebelle children (negatives), 1969 (Box 19, Folder 14)
  - Kathleen Winsor (negatives) (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Bradbury building (contact sheets and negatives) (Box 17, Folder 15)
  - Mojave, mule barn, etc. (photographic prints, contact sheets, negatives) (Box 17, Folder 14)
  - Cable cars (negatives) (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - San Francisco (photographic prints and contact sheets) (Flat-box 24, Folder 6)
  - Sutro Baths (negatives) (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - Utter McKinley, Los Angeles, etc. (contact sheets and negatives) (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - Watts Towers/Sam Rodia (negatives) (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - Muscle Beach (photographic prints) (Box 18, Folder 12)
  - Muscle Beach (contact sheets) (Box 18, Folder 13)
  - Cats (photographic prints, contact sheets, negatives) (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - Children's life (negatives) (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - Nuns' life (negatives) (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - Europe (photographic prints and contact sheets), 1957 (Flat-box 24, Folder 2)
  - Europe (negatives) (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - Europe (negatives), 1957 (Flat-box 24, Folder 3)
  - Europe (contact sheets), 1957 (Box 18, Folders 14-15)
  - Scandinavia, England, etc. (negatives) (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Paris, New York, etc. (negatives) (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Cairo, Eygpt - International Kinema Research (photographic prints) (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Yosemite trip (photographic prints), 1922 (Box 19, Folder 10)
  - Martha's Vineyard (photographic prints, contact sheets, negatives), 1965 (Box 19, Folder 11)
  - NH (negatives), 1964 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Summer (contact sheets and negatives), 1964 (Box 19, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous photographic prints and contact sheets, circa 1950-1965 (Box 20, Folders 1-3)
  - Miscellaneous negatives, circa 1950-1965 (Box 20, Folders 4-8)
  - Miscellaneous photographic prints (Box 21, Folders 1-11)
  - Miscellaneous contact sheets (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous negatives (Box 22, Folders 2-7)
  - Miscellaneous slides (Box 22, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous photographic prints (Flat-box 24, Folder 9)
- Series 7. Artwork
  This series contains miscellaneous artwork, including drawings, paintings, prints, and mixed media materials, as well as related clippings and ephemera. The works are mostly unidentified, but possibly by Ann Rosener, William Brice, Rico Lebrun, and others in her circle.
  - William Brice drawings; caricatures of Ann Rosener as a photographer (Flat-box 26, Folder 1)
  - Drawings; caricatures of Ambrose Perls (Flat-box 26, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous artwork (Flat-box 26, Folder 3)
  - Miscellaneous artwork (Flat-box 27, Folders 1-3)
  - Miscellaneous artwork (Flat-box 28, Folders 1-3)